<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>CPTSD Healing</title>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>This podcast is an audio-book-style reading of the works of "光瞳" on trauma healing, originally published on their Zhihu and WeChat official accounts. The creator of this podcast, a native of Hubei (湖北佬), found the information incredibly valuable for personal growth and wanted to make it accessible in an audio format for exercise and other activities.</p>
<p>The content delves into the complexities of CPTSD, offering a holistic approach to healing that integrates concepts from somatic experiencing, positive psychology, and an understanding of our innate pro-social nature. Through a series of chapters, this podcast explores:</p>
<ul>
<li>The foundational principles of self-help and trauma recovery.</li>
<li>The dynamics of interactive loops, perception, and emotional states.</li>
<li>A detailed examination of CPTSD, trauma, and the adaptation process.</li>
<li>Practical tools and techniques for self-regulation and healing.</li>
<li>The journey of self-conceptualization and "graduating" from CPTSD.</li>
</ul>
<p>This podcast also includes a study guide ("Ankis.md") and FAQs to help listeners deepen their understanding of the material. The goal is to share this freely available knowledge to aid others on their path to healing and self-discovery.</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://hubeilaocast.github.io/</link>
    <image>
      <url>https://HubeiLaoCast.github.io/img/CPTSD%20Healing.png</url>
      <title>CPTSD &amp; Asperger's Healing</title>
      <link>https://hubeilaocast.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    <generator>HubeiLaoCast RSS Generator</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 12:00:00 AEST</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://hubeilaocast.github.io/rss_en.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <author><![CDATA[Podcast by: hubeilaocast (湖北佬); Original Content by: 光瞳]]></author>
    <copyright><![CDATA[© 2024 hubeilaocast. The content of this podcast is based on the original works of 光瞳, shared freely on Zhihu and WeChat Official Account. All rights to the original content belong to 光瞳. This podcast is for educational and non-commercial use only.]]></copyright>
    <language><![CDATA[en-us]]></language>
    <itunes:author>Podcast by: hubeilaocast (湖北佬); Original Content by: 光瞳</itunes:author>
    <itunes:summary>This podcast is a study guide and audio adaptation of the insightful works on CPTSD and trauma recovery by the author 光瞳. It's designed for those who want to absorb this valuable information while on the go, whether you're jogging, at the gym, or simply taking a moment for yourself. Join hubeilaocast on a journey of learning and healing.</itunes:summary>
    <itunes:type>episodic</itunes:type>
    <itunes:owner>
      <itunes:name>hubeilaocast (湖北佬)</itunes:name>
      <itunes:email>contact@example.com</itunes:email>
    </itunes:owner>
    <itunes:explicit>No</itunes:explicit>
    <itunes:category text="Education">
      <itunes:category text="Self-Improvement"/>
    </itunes:category>
    <itunes:image href="https://HubeiLaoCast.github.io/img/CPTSD%20Healing.png"/>
    <itunes:new-feed-url>https://hubeilaocast.github.io/rss_en.xml</itunes:new-feed-url>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ch. 01: Foundations of Self-Help and Trauma Recovery]]></title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In this inaugural episode, we delve into the core concepts that underpin the journey of trauma recovery. We begin by examining the idea that pro-sociality is a fundamental human instinct, and how a lack of positive social interaction can lead to profound loneliness, even in the absence of a conscious awareness of it.</p>
<p>We then explore the vital concept of "self-responsibility," distinguishing it from the harmful notion of "victim-blaming." Taking responsibility is not about shouldering blame for the trauma itself, but about recognizing one's own agency and power in the healing process. This shift in perspective is essential for moving from a "victim" to a "survivor" mentality.</p>
<p>The episode also introduces two powerful psychological frameworks: the "Full Struggle Spirit," which helps us understand the all-or-nothing mindset that can hinder recovery, and the "Protracted War Spirit," which offers a more sustainable and compassionate approach to the long-term nature of healing. Finally, we touch on the "Hardware System" and "Software System" analogy to understand the interplay between our biology and our social experiences, as well as the "Continuum View" from positive psychology, which challenges rigid definitions of "normal" and "abnormal."</p>]]></description>
      <link>https://archive.org/details/beyond-symptoms-self-healing-cptsd-asperger-s-with-somatic-wisdom</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch01</guid>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[CPTSD &amp; Asperger's Healing Series]]></dc:creator>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 08:00:00 AEST</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://archive.org/download/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h/CPTSD%20%26%20Asperger%27s%20Healing%20-%20Ch.%2001_%20From%20Trauma%20to%20Triumph_%20Reclaiming%20Your%20Integrated%20Self%20for%20Self-Salvation.m4a" length="0" type="audio/mp4"/>
      <itunes:summary>This episode lays the groundwork for the entire series, exploring the fundamental principles of self-help and healing from trauma. We discuss the innate pro-social nature of humans, the crucial role of self-responsibility (without victim-blaming), and the shift in identity from "victim" to "survivor." This episode also introduces key concepts like the "Full Struggle Spirit" and the "Protracted War Spirit," providing a new framework for understanding the healing journey.</itunes:summary>
      <itunes:explicit>No</itunes:explicit>
      <itunes:duration>00:00:00</itunes:duration>
      <itunes:image href="https://archive.org/services/img/beyond-symptoms-self-healing-cptsd-asperger-s-with-somatic-wisdom"/>
      <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ch. 02: Understanding the Dynamics of Interaction and Perception]]></title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In this episode, we explore the fundamental concept of "interaction loops" and how they form the basis of our reality. We learn that every interaction, whether with our environment or with other people, creates a feedback loop that shapes our subsequent thoughts, feelings, and actions. This concept, borrowed from the Son-Rise Program for autism, provides a powerful lens for understanding how we develop and adapt.</p>
<p>We then break down the different levels of human activity, from the smallest "micro-activities" to the most complex "social activities." This hierarchical model helps us understand how our internal states, such as our emotions and physical sensations, influence our external behaviors, and vice versa. We also discuss the role of perception, and how our brains filter and interpret sensory information to create our subjective experience of the world.</p>
<p>Finally, we examine how trauma can disrupt these natural processes, leading to a disconnect between our internal and external worlds. We explore concepts like "emotional states," "behavioral impulses," and "conceptualization," and how they can become distorted in the aftermath of trauma. By understanding these dynamics, we can begin to identify the root causes of our struggles and develop more effective strategies for healing.</p>]]></description>
      <link>https://archive.org/details/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-02-unpacking-somatic-keys-to-healing-complex-trauma-and-aspergers</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch02</guid>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[CPTSD &amp; Asperger's Healing Series]]></dc:creator>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 09:00:00 AEST</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://archive.org/download/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h/CPTSD%20%26%20Asperger%27s%20Healing%20-%20Ch.%2002_%20The%20Exchange%20Loop_%20How%20Your%20Interactions%20Shape%20Reality%2C%20Emotion%2C%20and%20Healing.m4a" length="0" type="audio/mp4"/>
      <itunes:summary>This episode introduces the concept of "interaction loops" as the foundation for understanding all human experience. We explore how these loops shape our perceptions, emotions, and behaviors, both internally and in our relationships with others. The episode also breaks down the different levels of human activity, from micro-movements to complex social interactions, and examines how trauma can disrupt these processes.</itunes:summary>
      <itunes:explicit>No</itunes:explicit>
      <itunes:duration>00:00:00</itunes:duration>
      <itunes:image href="https://archive.org/services/img/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-02-unpacking-somatic-keys-to-healing-complex-trauma-and-aspergers"/>
      <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ch. 03: A Deeper Dive into CPTSD and the Nature of Trauma]]></title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In this episode, we take a closer look at the nature of trauma and its far-reaching effects on the human psyche. We begin by defining "stress" and "coping," and how the process of self-help involves using our agency to regulate our automatic stress responses. We then introduce the concept of "trauma" as a state of "stuckness" or "dissociation," where the natural stress response is unable to complete, leaving us in a state of chronic hyper- or hypo-arousal.</p>
<p>We then differentiate between "acute trauma" (Type I) and "complex trauma" (Type II), highlighting the unique challenges of recovering from chronic, relational trauma. We also explore the various "levels" of trauma, from "self-trauma" to "social trauma," and how these different experiences can interact and compound one another.</p>
<p>The episode concludes with a discussion of the relationship between CPTSD and Asperger's Syndrome (AS), and how the two conditions can be difficult to distinguish. We also touch on the developmental aspects of trauma, and how early life experiences can shape our vulnerability to trauma later in life. By gaining a deeper understanding of the mechanisms of trauma, we can begin to approach our own healing with greater compassion and clarity.</p>]]></description>
      <link>https://archive.org/details/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-02-unpacking-somatic-keys-to-healing-complex-trauma-and-aspergers</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch03</guid>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[CPTSD &amp; Asperger's Healing Series]]></dc:creator>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 10:00:00 AEST</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://archive.org/download/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h/CPTSD%20%26%20Asperger%27s%20Healing%20-%20Ch.%2003_%20Beyond%20Labels_%20Unpacking%20Complex%20Trauma%20and%20the%20Path%20to%20Healing.m4a" length="0" type="audio/mp4"/>
      <itunes:summary>This episode provides a detailed exploration of Complex Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (CPTSD), distinguishing it from classic PTSD. We examine the different types of trauma, from acute, single-event trauma to the chronic, relational trauma that characterizes CPTSD. The episode also discusses the comorbidity of CPTSD with other conditions, such as Asperger's Syndrome, and explores the developmental aspects of trauma throughout the lifespan.</itunes:summary>
      <itunes:explicit>No</itunes:explicit>
      <itunes:duration>00:00:00</itunes:duration>
      <itunes:image href="https://archive.org/services/img/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-02-unpacking-somatic-keys-to-healing-complex-trauma-and-aspergers"/>
      <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ch. 04: Practical Tools and Techniques for Self-Regulation and Healing]]></title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In this episode, we focus on the practical application of the concepts we've discussed so far, providing a toolkit of self-help strategies for managing the symptoms of CPTSD. We begin by exploring the importance of "biological rhythms," such as breathing, sleep, and digestion, and how we can use these natural cycles to regulate our nervous system.</p>
<p>We then delve into the world of "emotional regulation," and how we can learn to identify, understand, and manage our emotional states. We discuss the role of the "observer self," and how we can cultivate a compassionate and non-judgmental attitude towards our own inner experience. We also explore the concepts of "pendulation" and "titration," two key principles from Somatic Experiencing that can help us safely process traumatic memories without becoming overwhelmed.</p>
<p>The episode concludes with a discussion of the importance of "grounding" and "centering" techniques, as well as the role of "positive psychology" in cultivating resilience and well-being. By incorporating these tools into our daily lives, we can begin to create a sense of safety and stability from within, paving the way for deeper healing and transformation.</p>]]></description>
      <link>https://archive.org/details/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h_202509</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch04</guid>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[CPTSD &amp; Asperger's Healing Series]]></dc:creator>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 11:00:00 AEST</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://archive.org/download/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h_202509/CPTSD%20%26%20Asperger%27s%20Healing%20-%20Ch.%2004_%20Unlock%20Your%20Inner%20World_%20A%20Deep%20Dive%20into%20Trauma%20Healing%20and%20Self-Discovery.m4a" length="0" type="audio/mp4"/>
      <itunes:summary>This episode shifts from theory to practice, offering a range of practical tools and techniques for managing the symptoms of CPTSD and promoting healing. We explore the importance of biological rhythms, such as breathing and sleep, as well as the power of emotional regulation techniques. The episode also introduces the concept of "pendulation" and "titration" from Somatic Experiencing, and provides guidance on how to safely engage with traumatic memories.</itunes:summary>
      <itunes:explicit>No</itunes:explicit>
      <itunes:duration>00:00:00</itunes:duration>
      <itunes:image href="https://archive.org/services/img/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h_202509"/>
      <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ch. 05: The Journey of Self-Conceptualization and "Graduating" from CPTSD]]></title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In this concluding episode, we explore the ultimate goal of trauma recovery: to develop a new and empowering "self-conceptualization." This is not about creating a fictional narrative, but about weaving together the fragmented pieces of our experience into a coherent and meaningful whole. We discuss the importance of "meaning-making" in the healing process, and how we can find purpose and value in our struggles.</p>
<p>The episode then presents a series of "awakening moments" – vignettes and stories that illustrate the process of healing in action. These stories, which are based on real-life experiences, offer a glimpse into the transformative power of self-compassion, courage, and connection. From the "brave trembling" of facing one's fears to the "joyful reunion" of reconnecting with one's body, these stories provide a roadmap for the journey ahead.</p>
<p>Finally, we discuss what it means to "graduate" from CPTSD. This is not about being "cured" or "fixed," but about reaching a place of greater integration, resilience, and self-acceptance. We conclude with a message of hope and encouragement, reminding you that the journey of healing is a lifelong process of growth and discovery.</p>]]></description>
      <link>https://archive.org/details/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h_202509</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch05</guid>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[CPTSD &amp; Asperger's Healing Series]]></dc:creator>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 12:00:00 AEST</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://archive.org/download/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h_202509/CPTSD%20%26%20Asperger%27s%20Healing%20-%20Ch.%2005_%20Mapping%20Your%20Inner%20World_%20Graduating%20from%20Complex%20Trauma%20with%20Self-Conceptualization.m4a" length="0" type="audio/mp4"/>
      <itunes:summary>In this final episode of the series, we explore the process of "self-conceptualization," or developing a coherent and compassionate narrative of our own life story. We discuss how to integrate the insights gained throughout the healing journey into a new sense of self, and how to move from a place of "surviving" to one of "thriving." The episode concludes with a series of inspiring stories and metaphors to guide you on your continued path of growth and self-discovery.</itunes:summary>
      <itunes:explicit>No</itunes:explicit>
      <itunes:duration>00:00:00</itunes:duration>
      <itunes:image href="https://archive.org/services/img/cptsd-aspergers-healing-ch.-04-unlock-your-inner-world-a-deep-dive-into-trauma-h_202509"/>
      <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
